Beyond Journey's End
At the northernmost end of the continent,
I arrived at the place that
the people of this world call heaven:
Aureole, the land where souls rest.
Many souls gather there, and I spoke with
friends who once fought alongside me.
—Flamme the Legendary Mage
（ヒンメル）　フリーレン。
Frieren.
（フリーレン）　王都が見えてきたね。
The royal capital's in sight.
（ハイター）　私たち勇者一行の凱旋です
盛り上がっているでしょうね。
The adventurers are making
their triumphant return.
They must be celebrating in the city.
（ヒンメル）
帰ったら仕事　探さないとな。
We'll have to look for work once we're back.
もう　そんなこと考えているんだ。
You're already thinking about that?
（ヒンメル）　大事なことさ。
It's important, after all.
魔王を倒したからといって
終わりじゃ　ない。
We've defeated the Demon King,
but it's not over.
この先の人生のほうが長いんだ。
We have the whole rest
of our lives ahead of us.
（アイゼン）　仕事か…。
Work, huh?
酒が飲める仕事がいいですね。
I'd like something where
I can drink on the job.
（ヒンメル）　お前　僧侶だろ。
Aren't you a priest?
（ヒンメル：ハイター：アイゼン）　ハハハ…。
それもそうか。
I suppose you're right.
フリーレン　君のこの先の人生は➡
Frieren, the life ahead of you will surely
be much longer than we can imagine.
僕たちには想像もできないほど
長いものになるんだろうね。
そうかもね。
Perhaps.
Beyond Journey's End
（王様）　勇者ヒンメル➡
Himmel the Hero,
戦士アイゼン　僧侶ハイター➡
Eisen the Warrior, Heiter the Priest,
魔法使いフリーレン。
and Frieren the Mage.
こたびは
よくぞ魔王を打ち倒した。
Thank you for defeating the Demon King.
これで
世界に平和な時代が訪れよう。
Now our world will enter an age of peace.
（花火）
（子供たち）　ハハハ…。
王様が広場に　僕たちの彫像を
作ってくれるそうだ。
The king's going to erect
statues of us in the plaza.
まぁ　イケメンである　この僕を➡
I'm not sure they'll be able to faithfully
recreate my handsome looks, though.
忠実に再現できるかどうかは
甚だ疑問だがね。
現金なもんだ。
How self-serving of him.
旅立ちの時は　銅貨１０枚しか
くれなかったくせに。
He only gave us ten copper coins
when we left on our adventure.
まぁまぁ　フリーレン。
Now, now, Frieren.
Tonight, we drink for free.
こうして
タダ酒も飲めるわけですし➡
それでいいじゃないですか。
I'd say we're even, wouldn't you?
生臭坊主。
You corrupt priest.
ハッハッハッ…！
（アイゼン）　終わってしまったな。
It's over.
そうだね。
Yeah.
僕たちの冒険は　これで終わりだ。
This is the end of our adventure.
１０年ですか…
いろいろなことがありましたね。
It's been ten years, huh?
We've been through a lot.
（ハイターの声）　旅立ちの日に➡
The day we departed...
ヒンメルとアイゼンが
王様にタメ口　利いて➡
Himmel and Eisen were nearly executed
for speaking rudely to the king.
Kill them.
処刑されかけたり。
We'll give them a talking to.
Shall we lick your boots?
下手したら
あそこで冒険　終わってたよね。
One misstep, and our adventure
would've ended there.
ハイターが二日酔いで
役に立たなかったこともあったな。
Sometimes, Heiter was too
hungover to do anything.
｟あぁ　あぁ　あぁ…｠
｟アンデッドみたいな
顔色してるけど大丈夫？｠
You're as pallid as an undead.
Are you all right?
｟ダメ｠
｟ダメかぁ…｠
No.
No, huh?
（アイゼンの声）
週に１度は　そうだったからな。
It was a weekly occurrence.
その点　私は優秀。
I, on the other hand, was exceptional.
（アイゼンの声）
ミミックに食われかけた時は
置いてこうかと思ったぞ。
We thought about leaving you behind
when that mimic tried to eat you.
（ヒンメル）｟散々　罠だって言ったのに
マジかよ…｠
Seriously? We told her it was a trap.
It's dark and scary in here!
（アイゼン）
｟このエルフ　置いてかない？｠
Why don't we leave the elf behind?
（ヒンメル：アイゼン：ハイター）　ハハハ…。
まったく
クソみたいな思い出しかないな。
We have nothing but terrible memories.
でも楽しかったよ。
But I had fun.
僕は君たちと冒険ができて
よかった。
I'm glad I got to adventure with all of you.
そうですね。
Likewise.
短い間だったけどね。
It was a mere ten-year adventure.
短い？　何を言ってるんだ？
１０年だぞ？
"A mere ten-year adventure"?
But that's an entire decade
we spent adventuring together.
ハイターを見ろ　すっかり
おっさんになってしまったぞ。
Look at Heiter. He's turned into an old man.
失礼ですよ。
元からでしょ。
That's rude.
He always looked like that.
失礼ですよ。
That's rude.
（アイゼン）　そろそろか。
It's nearly time.
エーラ流星　でしたっけ？
The Era Meteor Shower, was it?
（ヒンメル）　５０年に１度の流星群。
It happens once every fifty years.
平和な時代の幕開けには
ちょうどいいな。
Perfect for marking the
start of an era of peace.
（ヒンメル）　キレイだな。
They're beautiful.
街中だと見えにくいね。
The view's not so good
from inside the city, though.
（ヒンメル）　人が感動しているんだ
空気を読みたまえ。
I'm having a moment over here.
Don't spoil the mood.
じゃあ　次。
ん？
Next time, then.
５０年後　もっとキレイに見える場所
知ってるから案内するよ。
I know a place where you
can see them more clearly.
I'll take you there in fifty years.
フッフフフ…。
何？
（ヒンメル）　いや　何でもない。
What?
It's nothing.
そうだな　みんなで見よう。
You're right. Let's go see them together.
じゃあ　私は　ここで。
Well, I should go.
これから　どうするつもりだ？
What are you going to do now?
魔法の収集を続けるよ。
I'm going to continue collecting spells.
１００年くらいは
中央諸国を巡る予定だから。
I plan to travel around the central lands
for the next hundred years or so.
まぁ　たまには顔を見せるよ。
I'll stop by once in a while.
エルフの感覚は分かりませんね。
I can't understand what
being an elf must be like.
まったく
いつから生きているのやら。
Seriously, how long has she been around?
５０年も１００年も➡
To her, fifty or even a hundred years
might be a trifling thing.
彼女にとっては
些細なものなのかもしれませんね。
（店主）　暗黒竜の角？
Shadow dragon horns?
うちでは取り扱ってないよ。
We don't have those here.
暗黒竜自体
２０～３０年は見てないね。
Haven't seen a shadow dragon
in twenty or thirty years.
そう…　困ったな　召喚に使うのに。
I see. That's no good.
I need one for summoning.
《そういえば
魔王城で拾ったやつ➡
Come to think of it, I think Himmel still has
the horn we got at the Demon King's castle.
ヒンメルに預けたままだっけ》
｟何か　邪悪なオーラみたいなの
出てるけど➡
It's exuding some kind of evil aura.
人体に害はないよね？｠
It's not harmful to people, is it?
｟分かんない｠
｟分かんないかぁ…｠
I don't know.
You don't know, huh?
《もうすぐエーラ流星の時期だし
ついでに取りに行くか》
It's nearly time for the
Era Meteor Shower again.
I'll pick the horn up when I visit him.
《前　来た時と
だいぶ町並みが違うな》
The city's changed quite a bit
since I was last here.
（ガチョウの鳴き声）
（子供）　ハァ　ハァ…　ふっ！
確か　ここら辺…。
It should be around here.
（ヒンメル）　フリーレン？
Frieren?
ヒンメル。
Himmel...
老いぼれてる…。
（ヒンメル）　言い方ひどくない？
You're so old.
Do you have to put it so bluntly?
年を取った僕も
なかなかイケメンだろ？
I'm still pretty handsome
at this age, though, aren't I?
５０年ぶりだね
君は昔の姿のままだ。
It's been fifty years.
You look the same as you ever did.
もう一生　会えないのかと
思っていたよ。
I thought I'd never see you again.
エーラ流星か　懐かしいね。
The Era Meteor Shower, huh?
That brings back memories.
あと　魔王城で
拾ったやつなんだけど。
About that thing we looted from
the Demon King's castle...
暗黒竜の角だね。
You mean the shadow dragon horn?
片時も忘れたことはないよ。
I've never forgotten about it.
ずっとタンスから
邪悪なオーラが出ていたからね。
My cabinet's been exuding
an evil aura all this time.
何か　ごめん。
Sorry, I think.
適当に納屋にでも放り込んで
おいてくれてよかったのに。
You could've stashed it
in a shed or something.
そうはいかないよ。
I couldn't do that.
君にとっては軽い気持ちで
預けたものかもしれないけど➡
You may not have thought much
of leaving it with me,
僕にとっては　大切な仲間から
預かった大事なものなんだ。
but to me, it was a treasure
entrusted to me by a dear friend.
いつか君に　こうして
返すべきものだったんだ。
I had to return it to you someday.
そんな大層なものじゃ
ないんだけどな。
It's not that big a deal.
（ノック）
（ドアが開く音）
ヒンメル　まだ？
Himmel, are you ready yet?
ハゲなんだから
こだわったって意味ないよ。
You're bald, anyway. There's no point
in fussing over your appearance.
ハゲなりのこだわりがあるの。
There are things we bald men
are particular about.
（ドアの開閉音）
では　エーラ流星を見に行こうか。
Now, shall we go see the Era Meteor Shower?
随分　貫禄が出たね　ハイター。
You've become rather dignified, Heiter.
聖都の司教ですから。
I'm a bishop of the holy city, after all.
あなたは全然変わりませんね。
You haven't changed at all.
ハッハッハ！
頭　なでんな。
Don't pat my head.
アイゼンは
あまり変わっていないね。
Eisen, you haven't changed much.
（アイゼン）　そうか　そう見えるか。
Is that how I seem to you?
さすがドワーフ。
I would expect as much from a dwarf.
（ヒンメル）　で　よく見える場所って
どこなんだ？
So, where's this place where we can
see the meteor shower clearly?
ん？
今から行くんですか？
We're going there now?
エーラ流星には　まだ時期が
少し早いと思いますが。
It's a bit early to see the
Era Meteor Shower, isn't it?
うん　だから
ここから１週間くらい歩いて。
Yeah. It's about a week's walk from here.
（アイゼン）　そんなに遠いのか。
It's that far away?
（ヒンメル）
まったく　老人を酷使しおって。
Unbelievable.
You should be kinder to the elderly.
（ヒンメルの声）　懐かしいよ。
This brings back memories.
こうしていると
あの時に戻ったかのようだ。
Traveling together like this makes me
feel like we've returned to those days.
（ヒンメルの声）
いろいろな所を旅したね。
We journeyed to all sorts of places.
何もかもが新鮮で
きらめいて見えた。
Everything seemed so brilliant and new.
（大きな足音）
（ヒンメルの声）
その美しい思い出の中には
いつも君たちがいた。
And you were always there
in those beautiful memories.
（ヒンメル）　僕はね➡
I'd been looking forward to the day
when we'd all be together again.
全員がそろう　この日を
待ち望んでいたんだ。
ありがとう　フリーレン。
Thank you, Frieren.
君のおかげで　最後に
とても楽しい冒険ができた。
Because of you, I had this delightful
adventure at the very end.
（ヒンメル）　キレイだ。
They're beautiful.
ヒンメルは
幸せだったと思いますよ。
I think Himmel was happy.
そうなのかな…。
You think so?
（参列者）　あの子
ヒンメル様の仲間なんだって？
She was one of Mr. Himmel's companions?
悲しい顔一つしないなんて。
I haven't seen her look sad once today.
（参列者）　薄情だね。
How heartless.
おやおや
私たちもしていませんよ？
Now, now! We're not wearing
sad expressions, either.
（参列者）　司教は真面目にやれ！
（参列者）　この薄情者！
Show some respect, Bishop!
You're heartless!
ハッハッハ　手痛いですな。
You wound me.
（鐘の音）
（土をかける音）
だって私
この人のこと何も知らないし…。
It's not like I knew anything about him.
（土をかける音）
たった１０年
一緒に旅しただけだし…。
We only traveled together
for a mere ten years.
（土をかける音）
人間の寿命は短いって
分かっていたのに…。
I knew human lives were short, but...
何で　もっと
知ろうと思わなかったんだろう。
Why didn't I try to get to know him better?
（泣き声）
頭　なでんなよぉ…。
Don't pat my head.
（馬車が近づく音）
では私も聖都に戻るとしましょう。
I should return to the holy city.
２人とも顔をよく見せて。
Let me get a good look at your faces.
これで最後になるでしょうからね。
This will probably be
the last time I see you.
どこか悪いの？
Are you unwell?
長年の酒が　たたりましてね。
My years of drinking have caught up to me.
（アイゼン）　天罰だな。
ハッハッハ！
It's divine punishment.
聖都に寄ることがあったら
私の墓に酒でも供えてください。
If you're ever in the holy city,
offer a drink at my grave.
ハイターは死ぬのが怖くないの？
Heiter, you're not afraid of dying?
私たちは世界を救った
勇者パーティーですよ。
We're the party of adventurers
that saved the world.
死後は天国で贅沢三昧に
決まっています。
We'll surely be living the good life
in Heaven after death.
そのために私は
あなた方と共に戦ったのです。
That's the whole reason
I fought alongside you.
生臭坊主。
ハッハッハ！
You corrupt priest.
それでは　お先に。
If you'll excuse me.
さて　私も　そろそろ行くよ。
I should get going, too.
魔法収集の旅か？
You're off to collect more spells?
うん　それもあるけど➡
There's that, too,
私は　もっと人間を知ろうと思う。
but I want to learn more about humans.
そうか。
I see.
それで１つ相談なんだけど
私　魔法職だからさ➡
So I wanted to ask you something.
Seeing as how I'm a mage, having a powerful
warrior to defend me would be a huge help.
強力な前衛がいると
助かるんだよね。
勘弁してくれ。
Give me a break.
もう斧を振れるような
年じゃないんだ。
I'm too old to swing an axe now.
そんな顔するな　フリーレン。
Don't make that face, Frieren.
人生ってのは衰えてからのほうが
案外　長いもんさ。
Surprisingly, life slows down
once you've lost your vigor.
そっか。
I see.
じゃあ　またね　アイゼン。
I'll see you later, Eisen.
ああ　また。
Yeah. See you later.
Episode 1: The Journey's End
さっきの木だ…
この森　いつも迷うな。
That's the tree I saw earlier.
I always get lost in these woods.
どこだ？　ここ。
Where am I?
20 years after the death of Himmel the Hero,
on the outskirts of the holy city of Strahl in the central lands
（フェルン）　何か　お探しでしょうか？
Are you looking for something?
どうかなさいましたか？
Is something the matter?
いや　ハイターって人の家を
探しているんだけど。
I'm looking for the home
of a man named Heiter.
では　お客様でございますね。
Then you're a visitor.
まだ生きてたんだ　生臭坊主。
ハッハッハ。
You're still alive, you corrupt priest?
カッコ良く死ぬのも
難しいものですな。
Turns out it's harder than I thought
to make a stylish exit.
墓に供える酒
買ってきちゃったけど　一杯やる？
I brought some liquor to offer at your grave.
Would you like a drink?
酒は　もうやめたんです。
そう。
I gave up drinking.
I see.
今更いい子ぶったって➡
I doubt the Goddess will forgive you
even if you clean up your act now.
女神様は
許してくれないと思うけどね。
ハッハッハ！
ありがとうございます。
Thank you.
あの子は？
フェルンといいます。
Who is she?
Her name is Fern.
南側諸国の戦災孤児でした。
She's a war orphan from the southern lands.
らしくないね。
It's not like you to
volunteer to help people.
進んで人助けするような
タチじゃないでしょ。
ヒンメルじゃあるまいし。
You're not Himmel, after all.
フリーレン　なぜ私の所へ？
Frieren, why did you come to visit me?
聖都への買い出しのついでだよ。
I was in the holy city
picking up some things.
旅先で会う人とは　なるべく
関わるようにしているからね。
I've been trying to get to know the people
I meet on my travels as much as possible.
それにハイターには
たくさん借りがあるから➡
And I owe you a lot, so I came to
repay my debts before you died.
死なれる前に返しに来た。
では１つ　頼み事を。
ん？
In that case, I have a request.
弟子を取りませんか？
Will you take on an apprentice?
フェルンには
魔法使いとしての素質があります。
Fern has potential as a mage.
あなたの旅に
連れていってくれませんか？
Will you take her with you on your travels?
ごめん　ハイター
それだけはできない。
I'm sorry, Heiter.
That's the one thing I can't do.
足手まといになるから。
She'd only get in my way.
実戦での見習い魔法使いの
死亡率は知ってるでしょ？
You know how often
apprentice mages die in battle.
友人から預かった子を
死地に送るつもりはないよ。
I'm not sending a child my friend
asked me to look after to her death.
そうですか。
I see. Then I have another request.
では別の頼みを。
（本を置く音）
賢者エーヴィヒの墓所から
出土したものです。
This was unearthed from
the tomb of Ewig the Sage.
この魔導書には
今は失われた死者の蘇生や➡
This grimoire is said to contain lost
spells of resurrection and immortality.
不死の魔法が
記されているとされています。
そんな魔法が
実在するとは思えないけど。
I find it hard to believe
such magic really exists.
それも含めて
解読をお願いしたいのです。
That's part of why I'd like you to decipher it.
できますか？
Can you do that?
絵を使った暗号でしょ？
It's written in code using pictures.
この時代の人は
こういうのが好きだね。
The people of this era
really liked this kind of thing.
まぁ　５～６年もあれば。
I could do it, given five or six years.
そうですか。
I see.
でも　こんなの解読して
どうすんのさ。
But why do you want this deciphered?
死ぬのは怖くないんじゃ
なかったの？
I thought you weren't afraid of dying.
理由は２つあります。
I have two reasons.
１つは　あなたたちの手前
格好をつけていたから。
The first is that I when I said that,
I was just putting on a brave face for you.
もう１つは
前より死ぬのが怖くなったから。
The second is that I'm now more
afraid of dying than I was before.
まぁ　不死とは言わず
ほんの少し…➡
Even if I can't achieve immortality,
I'd like a bit more time.
ほんの少しでいいから
時間が欲しくなったのです。
それに聖典には
健やかに生きよとあります。
Besides, the holy texts tell us
to live healthy lives.
長寿は　その最たるものですよ
フリーレン。
A long life is the ultimate
expression of that, Frieren.
生臭坊主。
ハッハッハ。
You corrupt priest.
それと
解読の片手間で構わないので➡
Also, in your spare time,
will you teach Fern magic?
フェルンに魔法を
教えてあげてはくれませんか？
私は僧侶なので
どうも勝手が分からないのです。
As a priest, I don't have that knowledge.
まぁ　そのくらいなら。
I could do that.
いた。
There you are.
捜すのが大変だったよ。
I've been looking everywhere for you.
いつも森で修行しているの？
Do you always train in the woods?
フリーレン様でも　私を見つけるのが
大変でございましたか？
Was finding me difficult even for you?
存在感が薄いと
ハイター様からも　よく言われます。
Mr. Heiter often tells me
I'm practically invisible.
とても良いことでございますね。
It's a very good thing, isn't it?
そうだね。
It is.
《やっぱり…　魔力探知に
ほとんど引っかからない》
It's true. I can barely detect her mana.
《卓越した魔力の操作技術だ》
Her control over her mana is exceptional.
《この年で一体
どれだけの研鑽を積んだんだ》
How much has she studied at such a young age?
ハイター様に➡
Mr. Heiter said when I can blast a hole
in that rock, I'll be a proper mage.
あの一番岩を打ち抜けば
一人前になれると言われました。
へぇ～
ハイターも分かってんじゃん。
Oh? Heiter knows what he's
talking about. That's—
あれはね…。
このように魔力が離散してしまい
届かないのです。
As you just saw, my magic
dissipates and doesn't reach it.
なるほどね。
I see.
どのような修行をすれば
よいのでしょうか？
What should I do to train?
ねぇ　先に１つ聞いていい？
Can I ask you something first?
魔法は好き？
Do you like magic?
ほどほどでございます。
Somewhat.
フッ。
私と同じだ。
Just like me, then.
Is Fern's training coming along smoothly?
Are you trying to put on
a brave face again, Heiter?
It saddens me to see him treated like this.
But they're worth looking for.
Magic sure is amazing, isn't it?
You keep collecting the strangest spells.
It'd be a waste for you to die.
Someday, I'd like to show them to you.
Episode 2
It Didn't Have to Be Magic...
It didn't have to be magic...